The Sahara Desert is well known as being
the world's largest hot desert, but its
sheer scale, emptiness, and isolation
might still surprise you anyway. Taking
up roughly a third of the entire African
continent, the Sahara Desert is slightly
larger than the contiguous 48th United
States. Or placed over Europe, it would
stretch over nearly the entire continent
from east to west. Across this whole
vast expanse of desert live only about 2
and a half million people today. And
there are large stretches throughout it
where you can travel for hundreds of
miles and never see another human, a
road, a tree, or even an animal. Wide
expanses of the desert larger than
entire European countries have
effectively zero permanent population.
Temperatures in the desert can soar up
to nearly 50° C during the summer. Water
is always incredibly scarce. the
landscape incredibly difficult to
traverse over, while dangerous
sandstorms can eliminate visibility to
only a few meters and bury roads
completely. The Sahara Desert might be
almost entirely empty of people today
for these reasons. But as it's only
recently started to become clear to us,
it's also absolutely full of incredible
secrets and mysteries just waiting to be
discovered that have been lost to time
buried beneath the sands. The Sahara
Desert, as it turns out, is one of the
most exciting unexplored frontiers
remaining on the planet for archaeology
in the 21st century. And there's far
more than you probably would have
expected that's been hidden there far
away from humanity for thousands of
years. So, let's peel back the layers,
see what's been hidden and found in the
Sahara, and what still remains
undiscovered and lost in the sands out
there just waiting for someone like you
to potentially find them.
During the Second World War between 1940
and 1943, the North African campaign
transformed the northern expanses of the
Sahara Desert into one of the busiest
aerial battlefields ever seen in the
world. [music] Germany and Italy battled
fiercely for aerial supremacy against
Britain and the United States. With tens
to even hundreds of thousands of sortes
between both sides spanning across a
vast area between Morocco in the west
and Egypt in the east. Thousands of
aircraft were lost between both sides
across the North African campaign. And
several hundred of those lost aircraft
have never been seen again. While many
of those lost aircraft almost certainly
went down in the Mediterranean Sea, an
unknown number of them also probably
vanished in the empty desert sea of the
Sahara. and many of them are probably
still waiting to be discovered out there
somewhere. Two especially famous
discoveries of lost World War II
aircraft in the Sahara hint at the
volume of possibilities that might still
be out there. The Lady Be Good was an
American B24D Liberator bomber with nine
crew members on board that was returning
back to its base in Libya following a
bombing raid on Naples, Italy carried
out in April of 1943.
The plane along with its whole crew
never ended up returning back to its
base. However, and for years it was
presumed to have crashed and vanished
somewhere in the Mediterranean Sea. The
bar's true fate wouldn't be revealed
until more than 15 years later after it
had disappeared. When in November of
1958, an oil exploration team from BP
that was operating in the remote deserts
of southern Libya just happened to
stumble upon the wreck of the Lady B.
good. In the middle of nowhere,
710 km deep inland away from the
Mediterranean.
Investigators who arrived at the crash
site later concluded that the nine-man
crew, who were all rookies out on their
first real combat mission, failed to
realize that they had overflown their
air base back in 1943 during a
sandstorm. Disoriented in the vast,
almost petrolless expanse of desert in
an age long before GPS, the crew then
continued to fly south deeper into the
desert for hours until they [music] ran
out of fuel when they parachuted out and
ditched the plane where it was
discovered by accident 15 years later in
1958.
Then a couple years later in 1960,
investigators managed to discover the
remains of eight of the nine missing
crewmen who were on board nearby, which
indicated that they had all likely
survived the initial crash. One can only
imagine the horrors and suffering those
nine men experienced after they crashed.
Stranded hundreds of miles away from the
nearest other humans in the middle of
the empty Sahara desert without [music]
any resources, struggling to survive
within an impossible environment until
they couldn't go on any longer. But at
least they had each other's company
going through it, which can't be said
for the other famous Sahara World War II
airplane discovery. In June of 1942,
British Flight Sergeant Dennis CPPing
was flying a lightly damaged P40
Kittyhawk fighter from the front line in
North Africa to a repair base due west
of Cairo. The aircraft was regarded as
flightw worthy despite the damage it had
suffered. But somewhere and somehow
during his flight, he flew off course
and simply vanished into the great
expanse of the desert. He was never
heard from or seen again and was
officially classified as one of the
countless men who went missing in action
during the course of the war. But then
an incredible 70 years after his
disappearance in May of 2012, a Polish
Oil Company employee who was working in
Egypt's western desert just happened to
accidentally stumble upon the wreck of
Coping's P40 Kittyhawk in the middle of
nowhere, roughly 320 km away from the
nearest town. The aircraft was so well
preserved in the dry desert environment
that the RAF Museum in London would
describe it as one of the best preserved
Second World War aircraft ever
discovered with one of the museum's
curators even going so far as to
describe it as the aviation equivalent
of Tuton Commons tube. Disturbingly,
however, investigators who arrived at
the crash site after its discovery
quickly concluded that Dennis CPPing
almost certainly survived his crash
landing. They found that the cockpit had
been opened, his parachute was rigged
nearby as a makeshift sun shelter along
with missing survival equipment that
would have been inside of the aircraft.
Like the pilots of the Lady Be Good,
CPPing had likely become disoriented and
lost while flying in the mostly
featureless desert and just kept flying
deeper inland until he ran out of fuel
and was forced to ditch. Unlike the crew
of the Lady Be Good, however, Coping was
entirely alone and left to himself
hundreds of kilometers away from any
kind of help. He crashed in such a
remote part of the Sahara that nobody
even knew where he was until seven
decades later. And much like the crew of
the Lady Be Good, we can only imagine
what horrors he experienced and dealt
with all alone out there with nothing
and no one to help. No remains
attributable to Dennis CPP have ever
been conclusively discovered, but there
are possible clues. A set of 12 human
bones were discovered about 3 miles away
from the crash site a few months after
it was found along with a fragment of
parachute fabric, a keychain fob with
the number 61 engraved on it along with
a metal button dated 1939.
This would strongly indicate that these
remains belong to coping, but it has
never been conclusively proven because
no DNA confirmation or formal forensic
identification has ever been publicly
made. It would probably be much stranger
if the bones discovered didn't belong to
coping because if they weren't his,
whose were they? And why were they found
to be so close to his crash site? On the
other hand, if they were his bones, why
were only 12 individual bones discovered
instead of a full skeleton? For now,
it's still an enduring mystery that the
Sahara has so far not yielded us a clear
resolution for. It is likely that much
more lost World War II aircraft and
their crews are still out there. Lost
somewhere in the empty desert after more
than 80 years now, patiently waiting all
of this time to become discovered after
decades of silence. Aerial surveys,
satellites, drones, and remote sensing
all might help find them and resolve the
fates of crews who have been listed as
missing in action for more than 80
years. But the North African campaign
battlefield spanned millions of square
kilometers where there are very few
roads and almost never any visitors
ultimately meaning that there are still
immense challenges towards finding these
tiny specks of airplanes across this
vast sea of shifting sand.
Relatively nearby to where Dennis coping
crashed in the Sahara desert of Egypt
lies the Wadi Alhitan or the Valley of
the Whales. roughly 150 kilometers or
three-hour drive southwest of Cairo,
which only recently has come to be
understood as one of the most important
paleontological sites ever discovered on
the planet. As its name suggests, the
Valley of the Whales is absolutely full
of whales, only long dead ones. More
than a thousand individual whale
specimens have been identified by
paleontologists here, which makes it the
largest whale graveyard ever discovered
anywhere. That might seem confusing to
you at first since the Valley of the
Whales is more than 100 miles away from
the nearest coastline and in the middle
of a desert. But around 40 million years
ago, the shapes of the Earth's
continents were very different from what
they are today. And back then, much of
North Africa, including the Valley of
the Whales, was submerged by the shallow
Tethus [music] Sea. The first fossilized
remains of whales in the valley, were
discovered all the way back in 1902.
[music]
But because of how remote the area was
and how difficult it was to actually get
there, the discovery attracted very
little attention or interest for most of
the rest of the 20th century. It wasn't
until the late 1980s when four-wheel
drive vehicles became more readily
available and reliable that significant
scientific interest in the Valley of the
Whales began.
And as it turned out, it was far more
important of a site than anybody
beforehand could have ever known.
Because of how the Teis Sea covered this
area tens of millions of years ago,
virtually all of the whale specimens
dated in the valley go back to sometime
around 37 to 40 million years ago. And
that makes them extremely unique from an
evolutionary perspective.
Historically, one of the biggest
mysteries in evolutionary biology was
simply the existence of whales.
Whales are air breathing mammals like
you and me. And they're four to five
times more closely related to us than
they are of fish. So scientists had long
hypothesized that whales had originated
on land but eventually went into the
water and gradually evolved into the
giants that we know today. But for a
very long time there wasn't any concrete
scientific proof of this until one of
the fossilized whale specimens at the
Wadi Al-Hitan was examined more closely
in 1989.
A specimen of the Basillosaurus
discovered in the valley, which dated to
between 40 and 37 million years ago, was
found that year to possess a pair of
very small hind legs complete with thigh
bones, shin bones, ankles, and
matchstick feet. No larger than a human
arm, these tiny hind legs would have
looked absolutely comical in a whale
that weighed six tons and would have
been completely useless for walking. But
finally, they provided scientists with
clear evidence of what had long been
suspected, that whales had indeed
originated on the land and then steadily
evolved to return back to the ocean
again. Thus, this unlikely spot in the
middle of the Sahara Desert became the
most important site on the Earth
[clears throat] for demonstrating the
evolution of the whales. And further
unknown marine life discoveries might
also still be waiting out there, too.
Life within the Sahara Desert has a
strange way of persisting despite the
incredibly hostile conditions.
All the way over in the center of the
Sahara Desert in northeastern Nishair
once stood what was probably the most
isolated tree in all of recorded
history. Known as the tree of Tanire, it
was a lone acacia tree that stood in the
desert roughly 400 km away from the
nearest other tree. It was so unusual
that it was used as a landmark by
caravan routes traveling across the
desert for centuries. And a well dug
nearby by curious French engineers in
the 1930s answered how it was able to
survive here. It turned out that the
treere's roots reached far enough down
to penetrate into the water table 33 to
36 m beneath the surface, which is how
it was able to sustain its life for so
long. But while it's not a mystery how
the tree was able to survive, how the
tree managed to get there and grow in
the first place, hundreds of kilometers
deep in the Sahara, far away from any
other vegetation, still remains obscure
and mysterious. And unfortunately,
[music]
after having survived for an estimated
300 years in this super remote location
against all the odds, the world's most
isolated tree no longer exists. Because
somehow, despite being the only obstacle
in any direction for hundreds of
kilometers of open sand, a drunk Libyan
truck driver still managed to crash into
the tree in 1973 and destroyed it,
ending its mysterious and interesting
centuries long story forever in an
instant. More than 1,600 km away to the
northwest from what used to be the
world's most isolated tree in the middle
of nowhere Algeria stands what still
might be the world's most isolated and
mysterious fortress.
This impressive structure standing
amongst the empty sands of the Saharaas
known only as the Casar draw of
Timamoon. Named after the closest modern
Algerian oasis town of Timamoon, roughly
50 km away and very very little is
actually known about it. The English
language Wikipedia article on this
structure only contains a handful of
sentences about it. While all of the
sources that are listed by Wikipedia all
just lead either to various pop science
articles of questionable reliability or
to a master's thesis in French that
discusses the site's architecture and
the role of tourism in designating
something a world heritage site. [music]
Out of the Pop Science articles that are
listed as sources on the Wikipedia page,
only one of them lists its own sources,
which include another Pop Science
article, a Quora Post, and a link to the
World Heritage website, where the Casar
draw of Tinamoon isn't even listed. One
of these articles does interestingly
discuss a team of Americans who
apparently researched the site back in
1980, but it also says that their
research was never published.
We ultimately don't even know who
constructed the Casar draw of Timamoon
or why or when or how. It's an enigma
whose origins have been completely lost
to time. The very limited information
that we do know about it is that it was
probably constructed sometime around a
thousand years ago. [music] It's made up
of two circular outer walls of clay,
sand, and straw that stand approximately
10 m high and 2 m thick. It contains a
single entrance. And there were no
exterior windows. Within the structure
are living spaces, community kitchens,
and a religious area believed to be a
mosque that are all spread out across
three separate levels. And that's about
all the knowledge we really actually
know about it. There is a severe lack of
archaeological research that has gone
into this place. And I hope that one day
a well-funded team gains the privilege
to really investigate it and potentially
crack open its secrets. But until then,
we'll never know who built this
structure and why or even how they did
so in such an incredibly remote and
barren location.
Moving on to our next stop in the Sahara
takes us to the far southern expanses of
Libya. Roughly 1,000 km south of the
Libyan capital of Tripoli in the region
of Fison. It is one of the most remote,
sparssely populated, and inaccessible
parts of the entire Saharan desert. And
amazingly, it's been hiding an
incredible secret for more than a
thousand years that has only recently
begun to be understood. In early 2011,
researchers from the University of
Leicester in England were able to use
modern satellite imagery to uncover the
remains of an entire dead civilization
in the desert sands that had been
forgotten about for millennia. The
satellite imagery revealed more than 100
fortified farms and villages with
castle-like structures along with
several towns all clustered densely
together in the middle of nowhere.
Initially, the researchers assumed that
these previously unknown forts uncovered
through their satellites hadn't been
built by the Roman Empire. But the ruins
were located well beyond the frontiers
of where the Roman Empire had existed in
North Africa. And a subsequent
archaeological field trip to the ruins
revealed that they were in fact the
ruins of a powerful native African
kingdom known as the Garamantes.
Many of the mud brick walls in the ruins
that the archaeologists discovered stood
as high as 3 to 4 m. While the
communities were found to have been
built somewhere between the 1st and
fifth centuries AD. The density of the
settlements in this area of seemingly
inhospitable desert was also just
astounding. The University of Leicester
archaeologist found that within just a
four square km area, there were at least
10 villageiz settlements complete with
agricultural field systems. wells,
cemeteries, and most peculiar of all,
the traces of a vast underground water
network that stretched for hundreds of
kilometers beneath the ground between
all of the various settlements. The
archaeologists had truly discovered one
of the holy grails of archaeology,
the remains of an entire civilization
that had simply been forgotten about and
lost a time. We know very little about
the Gamantes as a civilization.
Ancient Greek and Roman sources knew and
wrote about them, but they are vague and
derisive, treating them as nothing but
barbarians who are on the frontiers of
the known world. We know now, however,
that they were incredible engineers.
They managed to build an entire
civilization home to tens of thousands
of people in a region of the world that
receives effectively zero rainfall
through digging a vast network of
underground water channels known as
fogaras which transported ancient fossil
water from aquifers throughout their
numerous towns, castles, and villages in
the desert. Hundreds of these
subterranean water channels built by the
garamantes have been traced and
uncovered. And yet criminally little
about their civilization beyond that is
currently understood.
Unfortunately, almost immediately after
the University of Leicester team
discovered these ruins, Libya entered
into a period of immense geopolitical
instability that has made further
research into the Garamanti civilization
effectively impossible. The University
of Leicester team were only able to
conduct a rapid 5-day ground survey of
the ruins between January and February
of 2011, where they were able to visit
around 80 of the settlements that they
had discovered through their satellite
data, which is how they were able to
confirm through pottery samples that the
ruins indeed belong to the Garamantes
and were between 2,000 and,500 years
old. But they and nobody else have been
able to conduct any extensive excavation
since then because only weeks after they
arrived, Libya erupted into a full-scale
revolution and civil war and the country
has been gripped in permanent chaos ever
since. A second civil war in Libya
lasted between 2014 and 2020, and the
country has remained divided between two
rival governments since then, which has
made any further archaeological research
in Libya around the ruins of the
Gamantes impossible to manage without
compromising the researcher security.
The ruins still stand there, however,
abandoned and alone, just as they
seemingly always have been for the past
15 centuries.
And eventually, once Libya hopefully
returns back to a period of stability
again, archaeological research at the
site can also continue again and peel
back more of the secrets of this ancient
African civilization that the desert
continues holding.
There are, of course, other lost relics
of the ancient world that might still be
able to be discovered hidden in the
Sahara as well, but we're not really
sure if the most famous possibilities of
them even exist at all. The famous
ancient Greek historian Heroditus wrote
in the fifth century BC about a massive
Persian army 50,000 men strong who
marched into the western desert of Egypt
in 525 BC on a campaign of conquest
under the orders of the Persian king
Kesus II who supposedly became engulfed
in a sandstorm and were never seen or
heard from again. Herodotus' account of
this story is however the only ancient
source that we have of this event. And
Herodotus wrote about it 75 years after
it supposedly had happened. Many
searches for the remains of this lost
Persian army in Egypt's western desert
have been made over the previous
decades, but to date, no evidence or
trace of it has ever been made. And
there's good reason to doubt the
authenticity of Herodotus' account of it
in the first place. Herodotus is rather
infamous for overexaggerating the
details and numbers involved in the
stories he wrote about. And his figure
of 50,000 Persian soldiers getting lost
in the desert is almost certainly no
exception. The mainstream archaeological
consensus today is that the lost army of
Kimpes probably actually happened in
some way or another, but it was almost
certainly fewer than 50,000 men. While
the entire army getting swallowed up by
a devastating sandstorm is probably not
entirely accurate either. The army may
have gotten it destroyed during a
military engagement or ran out of
supplies in the desert and simply wasted
away. Nonetheless, it is still among the
ancient world's most famous disappeared
stories and mysteries. And despite the
reasonable doubts, there's still a
chance that it might still be able to be
found out there somewhere, [music]
especially with recent advances in
satellite imagery, drone surveys, and
ground penetrating techniques.
And curiously, the lost army of Gibbs
isn't the only potential relic of the
ancient world that could still be lost
somewhere in the Sahara. One of the
strangest currently unsolved mysteries
in the world of Egyptology is the fate
and final resting place of the ancient
pharaoh Ramsy's VII.
Ramsy's VII was a pharaoh of ancient
Egypt's 20th dynasty who ruled briefly
for only about 1 year between 1130 and
1129 BC. And curiously, he is the only
pharaoh belonging to the 20th dynasty
whose tomb and mummy have never been
definitively identified anywhere within
the valley of kings or elsewhere. Every
single other pharaoh who belonged to his
dynasty has an accounted for tomb. And
so the potential discovery of his tomb
has long been considered to be one of
the holy grails in modern Egyptology.
There are broadly considered to be three
different possibilities when it comes to
his missing tomb. The first is that his
tomb does in fact exist, but has simply
never been found yet. It might lie
beneath flood debris. It could be placed
beneath later tomb construction. The
entrance may have been buried by ancient
rock slides, or it may rest in a portion
of the valley of the kings that hasn't
yet been fully excavated. The tomb of
Ramsy's VII could be like that of Tudin
Commons tomb whose low position dug into
the floor of the Valley of the Kings
allowed for its entrance to become
obscured by years worth of debris
deposited by flooding in later tomb
construction which led to the location
of Tuden's tomb becoming similarly lost
to history for thousands of years until
it was discovered again in modern times
in 1922.
Ramsy's VI's tomb could still be hidden
in a similar manner. But it's also
possible that because his reign was so
short, his tomb could have also been
started but never actually completed,
which would make it much more difficult
to recognize today. While he also could
have been buried in an already existing
tomb. And while the location of his tomb
and mummy might still remain a mystery,
archaeologists have nonetheless made
other incredible recent discoveries in
the deserts of Egypt with the help of
modern technology like infrared
satellite surveys. In May of 2011,
Egyptologists affiliated with the
University of Alabama, led by Dr. Sarah
Parkak announced to the world that they
had revealed more than a thousand tombs,
3,000 ancient settlements, and most
interestingly of all, 17 potentially
lost pyramids in Egypt after looking
through infrared images they had taken
through satellites. Over the years that
have followed that announcement, only a
handful of the sites have been properly
investigated and excavated. While Dr.
Parkak has observed that the visible
archaeological record in Egypt is likely
only a small fraction of what survives
buried beneath the Nile's flood plane
that her team is still helping to
uncover. And expanding even further on
her point, the visible archaeological
record all across the Sahara is likely
only a small fraction of what survives
buried beneath the sand. Because more
recently than most of us assume, the
Sahara Desert didn't even exist at all.
and it was covered by lush green
vegetation that was dramatically more
habitable instead.
This is all something that we've
basically only just begun to really
grasp and understand. And it all comes
down to how the Earth moves through the
cosmos.
We all know that our planet rotates once
roughly every 24 hours and then it makes
one full revolution around the sun
roughly every 365 days. But what is less
wellknown is how the Earth also slowly
wobbles during its rotation like a
spinning top would. A process that's
known as procession. The rate of the
Earth's procession or wobble varies
along a 21,000year time scale. And this
is directly linked to the cycles that
the Sahara region experiences.
When the Earth is wobbling on its axis
at different times along this 21,000year
cycle, the seasons will alternate
between being more or less extreme in
the northern and southern hemispheres.
When the wobble results in the northern
hemisphere being tilted closer to the
sun, there is an increase in the amount
of solar radiation hitting the tropics,
which adds fuel to the west and east
African monsoon systems. It results in
the East African monsoon summer rains
increasing over the Ethiopian highlands
and the upper Nile while it
simultaneously also results in the West
African monsoon system to pour summer
rains from the Atlantic all over the
Sahara. The result is that during these
periods of time when the northern
hemisphere is tilted more closely to the
sun, the Sahara basically turns green
and humid with huge swaths of lush
savannah vegetation in plentiful flowing
rivers and lakes. The last time that the
Sahara was in this green phase, also
known as an African humid period, was
roughly between 14,000 and 5,500 years
ago before the present, which
geologically speaking was not that long
ago. This was a roughly 8,500year period
in the not tooistant past where the
Sahara looked absolutely nothing like it
does today before the Earth's wobble
shifted again and disrupted the monsoons
in Africa and caused the Sahara to begin
drying out again into the desert than
has existed for virtually all of
recorded human history. But thousands of
years worth of unrecorded human history
took place in this green Sahara before
it returned back to the desert. And
we're really only just now starting to
understand what could actually be lost
there buried beneath the sands today.
What's especially interesting is that we
now know the Sahara has been alternating
in these cycles between green, lush,
humid savannah and dry aid desert for
millions of years. Over the past roughly
8 million years, it's believed that this
cycle has repeated about 230 separate
times between savannah and desert in the
Sahara. And it's believed that in about
9,000 more years in the future from now,
it'll gradually begin returning back to
a green savannah again, just as it
always has been for ages now. We now
know that during the last green phase of
the Sahara between 14,000 and 5,500
years ago, the geography of the region
was staggeringly different in almost
countless ways than it is today. Lake
Chad, for example, at the junction of
the modern-day countries of Chad,
Nijair, Nigeria, and Cameroon was
dramatically bigger back then than it is
now. About 7,000 years ago, when the
Sahara was green and humid, Lake Chad
encompassed a massive area of around
400,000
square kilometers, roughly 100 times
larger than it is today. It was so big
that scientists have referred to its
form back then as Lake Mega Chad, my
favorite name for a geographic feature
that I've ever heard of. Lake Mega
Chad's depth exceeded more than 180 m
and at its greatest extent, it was
likely the largest lake in the world and
possibly one of the largest lakes that
has ever existed anywhere on the Earth's
surface in the planet's history. It was
slightly larger than the modern-day
Caspian Sea is between Asia and Europe,
and it was nearly twice as large as all
of the great lakes in North America
combined.
One can truly appreciate Lake Mega
Chad's size when you place Athetheria
over the United Kingdom in Ireland and
see just how much both of them the lake
would cover. And curiously, located
relatively close by to where the ancient
shoreline of Lake Mega Chad once
extended to exists what is so far the
greatest modern discovery and insight
into the human inhabited world of the
Green Sahara ever made to date. at a
place known as Goberro in Marishair.
Today, Goberro is an utterly barren
landscape almost completely devoid of
rain and covered by massive shifting
seas [music] of sand, where the
temperature often soarses past 48° C or
120 Fahrenheit. It's a remote and
inhospitable location where nobody
expected to find anything significant of
archaeological value. But in the year
2000, a team of paleontologists led by
Professor Paul Sereno [music]
from the University of Chicago just
happened to be in the area in a convoy
of Land Rovers searching for dinosaur
fossils. They were not archaeologists
searching for the remains of ancient
human activity. But by random freak
chance, [music]
just as their convoy was preparing to
return back to their camp, the
expedition's photographer, Mike Hetwer,
walked away from the rest of the team
toward three small dunes he had spotted.
And once he got there, he immediately
saw that they were covered with human
bones, arrowheads, beads, and stone
artifacts.
What he had accidentally stumbled upon
was in fact the largest graveyard that
has so far ever been discovered in the
Sahara and the clearest window we've
ever found into the world of the Green
Sahara that predates our recorded
history. As it turned out, [music] Goa
was almost continually inhabited by
ancient humans for a period of around
5,000 years between about 8,000 BC and
3000 BC. Throughout the period when the
Sahara was last known to be green, over
six archaeological expeditions to Goro
that followed its 2000 discovery, a
literal treasure trove of information
was managed to be gleaned from it. At
least 182 burial sites have so far been
uncovered there, and at least [music] 67
of them have so far been excavated. The
oldest of them was a tall 6'2 man who
had been tightly [music] bundled
together and buried around 9,500 years
ago before the present. While the
youngest of them was a 10-year-old girl
buried around 4,900 years ago before the
present, who was discovered with a
bracelet around her arm made out of a
hippo tusk. The length of time between
these two discovered burials, roughly
5,000 years, is absolutely astonishing
when you consider how close together
they were found. It also appeared that
the site was inhabited at separate times
by two different distinct [music]
cultures. The older burials appear to
have belonged to a fishing foraging
culture that the archaeologists have
called the Kifians, while the younger
burials belong to a separate hering
culture that the archaeologists have
called the Tenarians.
Among the dozens of ancient burials
between both cultures discovered at
Goberrow, one of the most intriguing is
one that was discovered in 2006,
consisting [music] of three skeletons
buried together on their sides, all
holding hands. It was found that one of
the skeletons belonged to an adult
woman, while the other two belonged to
young children aged between 5 and seven.
While there has never been any immediate
proof of [music] this, it has been
assumed that this burial belonged to an
ancient mother and her two children who
met some unknown tragedy in the Green
Sahara in the very distant past. There
are no signs of trauma on any of the
bones, while their teeth also signaled
that they were all in good health at the
time of their passing. Some have
speculated that they were the victims of
a drowning, which seems odd today when
looking at the area and how it's
hundreds of kilometers away from any
large body of water. But immediately
adjacent to the dunes where the team led
by Sereno initially found Goro, they
found evidence of a dried up lake bed
that was likely full of water thousands
of years ago back when the Sahara was
green and Go was inhabited. There was
further evidence found around the site
that suggests the area once had abundant
water, too. Big piles of bones belonging
to fish, crocodiles, turtles, giraffes,
and hippos were all found around Goro as
well, along with trash heaps full of the
bones of catfish and muscle shells.
Large fish hooks and harpoon points were
discovered along with ceramic pots
depicting aquatic environments.
For thousands of years, long before
recorded history began, generation after
generation of people just like you and
me lived out all of their lives here
with all of their loves and their
tragedies in an abundant environment
that was completely unlike the way the
area looks today. And then after
remaining there more or less continually
for thousands of years, the people who
lived there suddenly abandoned it and
moved on for greener pastures elsewhere
as the Sahara shifted back into its
desert form around 5,000 [music] years
ago, leaving behind all of their
millennia of history in the region to be
buried by the encroaching sands that
obscured everything they had left
behind. a secret that became lost to
time and that was held tightly by the
Sahara until after 5,000 years later.
Another man who was in the right place
at the right time just happened to
discover it in the same year that George
W. Bush won his presidential election
against Al Gore. It's absolutely
incredible. But unfortunately, as is so
common with these incredible discoveries
that are happening in the Sahara, the
geopolitical environment is making
further discoveries and excavations
extremely difficult. In 2023, a military
coup overthrew the democratically
elected government in Nishair. And the
year later, the new government ordered
that the US and French militaries leave
the country for good. Swaths of the
country have fallen under the control of
radical jihadist factions and
insurgencies. [music]
And to replace the French and the
Americans, the new government in Nijair
has brought in Russia's Africa Corps to
battle against them instead. All of
which means that it's very unclear when
or even if Western archaeologists will
ever be able to safely return and
continue excavations at Goro or anywhere
else in Nishair again. And there are
probably countless other locations just
like Goro that are still out there
dotted all across the sands of the
Sahara and potentially things that are
even more incredible. Consider the site
of Gobeci.
First discovered in the 1960s in
modern-day Turkey, an extensive village
covered by megalithic stone buildings
and artifacts that was built and
inhabited between 9,500 BC and 8,000 BC.
lining up exactly with when the Sahara
was still green. While Bbec is in
Turkey, its age proves that humans were
building megalithic structures somewhere
at the same time when the Sahara was
green, which to my mind implies that
similar unknown Neolithic settlements
might still be hidden somewhere out
there in the Sahara as well. Nearly all
ancient civilizations that began arising
around 5,000 years ago, about precisely
when the Sahara began shifting back into
a desert again, did so around river
valleys. Like the Egyptians along the
Nile, the Mesopotamians along the
Tigress and Euphrates, the Endus River
Valley civilization, and the Chinese
along the Yellow and Yang Sea.
Mesopotamian civilization in particular
began arising in the fertile crescent
between the Tigris and Euphrates around
6,000 years ago before the present when
the Sahara was still within its green
phase. If you were going to try and
search for a lost civilization that
might have also arisen somewhere in the
Sahara when it was still green or at
least more lost settlements like Goro,
the best location to bet on would be
along major river valleys. In the
current day, the Sahara only has two
permanently flowy rivers that cross it,
the Nile and the Nger. But very, very
recently, scientists have also uncovered
that during the Green Sahara period,
there was an even bigger river than
either of these that also crossed the
Sahara as well that was simply lost to
time. The first clue of this dead
river's existence was uncovered by an
oil company that was searching for
offshore oil reserves just off the coast
of Moritania. [music] During their
searches, they discovered a previously
unknown gigantic deep sea canya that
began just off of Cape Timmerous in
Moritania that extended for a whopping
400 km with a width of 2 1/2 km and a
depth that reached nearly 1 kilometer
below the seafloor in waters up to 3 km
deep. Deep sea canyons like this
immediately off of a shoreline are
always formed and carved where a major
river empties into the sea. But
curiously, no major river anywhere near
large enough to have created it exists
today remotely nearby the area. There is
nothing but dry, arid sand and desert
for hundreds of kilometers in every
direction of where the canyon begins off
the coast of Moritania, which gave
geologists an unsolved mystery for more
than a decade. It wouldn't be until
[music] 2015 when researchers began
putting the pieces together that finally
solved the mystery. With the help of a
Japanese orbital satellite that made use
of microwave radar sensing, a team of
French researchers were able to see
below the sands of the Sahara to detect
a web of ancient fossil water that was
still present that helped uncover the
path of the ancient and long deadad
river system that emptied out into the
canyon off of Cape Timmerous that
[music] has since been called the Taman
Racet. And calling it a huge river would
be a criminal understatement.
Winding its way to Cape Timmerous from
its source in the southern Atlas
Mountains and Hogar Mountains in what is
now Algeria more than 500 kilometers
inland. [music] The Tamman Rassid River
once drained a watershed in West Africa
that was roughly the same size as the
Ganges Brahmaputra wershed in South
Asia. And if it contained a similar
flow, it would have had the second
largest flow of any river on the African
continent, exceeding both the Nile and
Nijair rivers that still flow across the
Sahara today and remaining only behind
the colossal flow of the Congo River
continentwide.
If the Tam Rasid River system still
existed today, it would rank as the 12th
largest on the entire planet. And it's
frankly astonishing that such a major
geographic feature was only discovered a
little more than a decade ago in 2015.
Interestingly, the Tamag Rasid River has
probably not flowed continuously for
millions of years like other rivers
have, but activates and deactivates
again cyclically over tens of thousands
of years along with the rest of the
Sahara as it alternates between green
and desert periods. It's likely that
over the past several million years, the
Tamr Rasid River has alternated between
massive gorging river and dried up
desert riverbed hundreds of times. And
it almost certainly flowed during the
last time the Sahara was green between
14,000 and 5,500 years ago before the
present. And because we've only known
about this giant river's existence and
its cyclical nature since 2015,
virtually zero archaeological research
has ever gone into the area around it so
far. With what we know and have
discovered around the Goro site, it's
almost a certainty that humans lived
alongside the banks of the Tamr Rasset
River during the last Green Sahara
period, too. And it might even be
possible that some kind of proto
civilization might have developed along
its banks too before the Sahara and the
river dried up and the area became
abandoned and lost a tie. Especially
when you consider that megalithic sites
like Obey in modern-day Turkey and the
first traces of ancient Mesopotamian
civilization arose at the same time as
the Tamman Rasset River was still
flowing strong. I think it's just
entirely [music] a coincidence, but it's
also at least a little bit curious and
funny that almost immediately adjacent
to where the Tamman Rasid River once
flowed is also the Rashhat structure or
the eye of the Sahara, a gigantic eroded
geological dome that is one of the most
visible geographic features on the
Earth's surface from space. The fringe
[music] theories have long tried to
suggest was the ancient prehistorical
site of Atlantis. It would be truly
incredibly funny and ironic if these
fringe theories were actually sort of
correct. And a different previously
unknown lost civilization in the Sahara
actually was discovered somewhere nearby
the Richhat structure along the dead
banks of the Tam Racet River instead.
Who knows what ultimately might still be
hiding out there, but performing
archaeological research into the area
around the Tamar Rasut River is going to
be yet again incredibly complicated
because of modern-day geopolitics.
Some of the ancient river's course
extends through the controversial
territory that's usually referred to as
Western Sahara, where a complex war is
currently taking place between Morocco,
who claims the entire territory, and the
indigenous Saharawi people, who assert
their right to self-determination and
independence.
The conflict in western Sahara has been
ongoing for decades now, and the area
between Moroccan controlled territory
and Saharawi controlled territory is
separated by a massive wall and millions
of landmines.
International journalists have referred
to Morocco's administration in Western
Sahara as being effectively a police
state, and armed violence between the
Moroccan army and the Saharawi's armed
political wing are still frequent
occurrences since the ceasefire between
them ended in 2020. All of this means
that properly investigating all of the
potential areas around the Tamar Raset
River for signs of life or civilization
from the last Green Sahara period might
be geopolitically impossible for quite
some time until the Western Sahara
conflict is finally resolved or dies
back down again, which might not be for
a very long time. So, in the end, the
Sahara might continue holding on to its
countless remaining secrets from us for
a great deal longer.
The Sahara continues to be full of
surprises, but one thing that's also
always surprised me is how many people
just accept banking fees as something
that's unavoidable. Monthly maintenance
fees, overdraft fees, minimum balance
requirements, they become so normal that
a lot of us don't even question them
anymore. But that's one of the reasons
why I was interested in this video
sponsor, Chime. Instead of making money
from those kinds of fees, Chime is built
around helping you keep more of your own
money while giving you tools that
actually help you move forward
financially. The feature that stood out
to me the most is their new Chime card.
It's a secured Visa credit card that
lets you build your credit using your
own money, so you're never spending more
than you've already set aside. If you're
someone who's been hesitant about
traditional credit cards because of debt
or overspending, it's a really different
and interesting approach. But that's
only one part of it. [music] When you
set up qualifying direct deposits, Chime
also gives you access to features like
getting paid up to 2 days early, earning
5% cash back on a category of your
choice, and 3.75%
APY on your savings. You also get access
to more than 47,000 feef free ATMs
nationwide. And there were no monthly
fees, no overdraft fees, or minimum
balance fees. If you're looking for a
smarter way to manage your money, or if
you're just tired of paying overdraft
fees, it's definitely worth taking a
look. You can go to
chime.com/realifeelore
or click the link down in my description
to learn more about Chime. That's
chime.com/realifeif.
Doing so will also help out supporting
my channel tremendously. And as always,
thank you so much for watching.